<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Project IDX - Blog</title><description>Project IDX is an entirely web-based workspace for full-stack application development, complete with the latest generative AI (powered by Codey and PaLM 2), and full-fidelity app previews, powered by cloud emulators.</description><link>https://idx.dev/</link><language>en-us</language><item><title>Build with Gemini models in Project IDX</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/build-with-gemini-in-idx/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/build-with-gemini-in-idx/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, we &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/blog/article/introducing-android-emulators-ios-simulators-and-other-product-updates-from&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a series of product updates to Project IDX to help streamline and simplify full-stack, multiplatform software development. This week, we’re excited to share how Project IDX uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-gemini-ai/&quot;&gt;Gemini models&lt;/a&gt; to provide you with AI features to further speed up and refine your end-to-end developer workflow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Project IDX launched with support for AI-powered code completion, an assistive chatbot, and contextual code actions like “add comments&amp;#39;&amp;#39; and “explain this code” to help you write high-quality code faster. Since launch, and thanks to your feedback, we’ve been working hard to add new AI functionality to help boost your productivity even more. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Work faster with inline AI assistance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can now get &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/idx-ai-inline&quot;&gt;inline AI assistance&lt;/a&gt; inside any file by pressing Cmd/Ctrl + I. Simply describe the changes you want to make to your code and IDX inline AI assistance will provide real-time error correction, code suggestions, and auto-completion in your code. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We integrated these AI enhancements directly into Project IDX’s centralized workspace to equip you with the necessary tools and resources for full-stack app development where and when you need them. From setting up your workspace to testing your app, IDX AI assistance helps accelerate and improve your workflow, ensuring that your end-to-end development experience is faster, easier, and higher quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, let’s say you want to add an authenticated API endpoint to your server. You can tell IDX AI to write the code necessary to enable secure task management using Firebase Authentication and Cloud Firestore. Given an input prompt, IDX AI assistance can write the code to construct the route, determine which APIs to use to verify the token, and save the data to the database. Instead of writing boilerplate code, you can focus on higher-level design and problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, let&amp;#39;s say you want to clean up your code a bit to improve its quality, readability, and maintainability. IDX AI assistance can help you quickly and easily refactor your code, so you can get right into optimizing your work without the hassle of manual refactoring. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And, as you wrap up your project, IDX AI can help you test and debug your code to make sure your application is running smoothly before deployment. Tell IDX AI assistance to write you a unit test for a function to ensure it’s working properly, saving you time and effort as you inspect the quality of your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Easily add AI features with the Gemini API template&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re also simplifying the process of building with the Gemini API with &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/build-gemini-api-app&quot;&gt;Project IDX’s new Gemini API template&lt;/a&gt;. The Gemini API template uses the Gemini Pro model to embed AI-powered features into your applications without additional configuration on your end, so you can get started working with the Gemini API quickly and easily. There&amp;#39;s even an option to use the Gemini API via the popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.langchain.com/&quot;&gt;LangChain&lt;/a&gt; framework to simplify the process of building LLM-powered apps. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gemini API template is multimodal, meaning it can provide context-aware prompt output for a myriad of input modalities including images, text and, of course, code. This can help you add features like conversational interfaces, summarization of user reviews, translation, and automatic image caption creation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate its functionality, we pre-configured the Gemini API template with ‘Baking with the Gemini API’, a recipe builder application that, using the Gemini model’s multimodal capabilities, can reverse-engineer possible recipes for baked goods from just a picture. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But this recipe builder is just one example of the Gemini API template in action – with support for different input modalities and context-aware output generation, you can use IDX’s Gemini API template to create a myriad of innovative and impactful applications that deliver AI-enhanced experiences to your users. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Stay tuned for more AI updates &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;These updates are a continuation of our efforts to leverage Google’s AI innovations for Project IDX, so make sure to keep an eye out for more announcements to come, including the expansion of AI in IDX to more than 150 countries/regions in the coming weeks. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your continued support and engagement – please keep the feedback coming by &lt;a href=&quot;https://issuetracker.google.com/issues/new?component=1379083&amp;template=1836320&quot;&gt;filing bugs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com/forums/953956-general&quot;&gt;feature requests&lt;/a&gt;. For walkthroughs and more information on all the features mentioned above, check out our &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/introduction&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t already, &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/&quot;&gt;visit our website&lt;/a&gt; to sign up to try Project IDX and join us on our journey. Also, be sure to check out our new &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/blog&quot;&gt;Project IDX Blog&lt;/a&gt; for the latest product announcements and updates from the team. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can’t wait to see what you create with Project IDX! &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Post</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/ios-simulator-video/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/ios-simulator-video/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Giving you in-browser access to an iOS simulator is definitely one of the bigger features we announced with Project IDX last week!  
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This simulator isn&amp;#39;t just for mobile apps, it&amp;#39;s great for web apps too. Check out the video below that shows how easy it is to test a web app across desktop and mobile devices!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Nix + IDX: Flexibility + extensibility in your workspace</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/nix-on-idx/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/nix-on-idx/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Over here on &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/&quot;&gt;Project IDX&lt;/a&gt;, we like to work fast. A big part of that means making sure we’re building the tools we need to increase efficiency and streamline the grunt work that hampers our velocity. As developers coding in a browser-based workspace, one of the pain points we felt keenly was the startup cost of setting up a new workspace with all the dependencies we needed, and the environment configuration we wanted. So, one of our priorities in building IDX was to address that pain point with streamlined workspace configuration — which we did by building Nix into IDX. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;How does Nix fit into IDX?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://nixos.org/manual/nix/stable/introduction&quot;&gt;Nix&lt;/a&gt; to define the environment configuration for each workspace. Nix is a purely functional package manager that assigns unique identifiers to each dependency, which ultimately means your environment can contain multiple versions of the same dependency, seamlessly. However, for us, the extensibility, programmatic configuration and effective environment caching we get from Nix provides the biggest payoff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nix is also reproducible and declarative. In the context of IDX, this means you can share your Nix configuration file across workspaces to load the same environment configuration. IDX defines the preview environment and workspace package configurations directly in the code repository with the &lt;code&gt;.idx/dev.nix&lt;/code&gt; file. So, if you want to jumpstart your pair programming, you can share your Nix configuration file as part of your code repo and your teammates can dive right in with minimal setup. This is also a cornerstone of how we build templates for a wide variety of frameworks and languages in IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re familiar with Nix, however, you might notice that our implementation doesn’t follow a strictly traditional Nix model. We built Nix into IDX workspaces as a way to manage packages and configure VM environments attached to them, not as a pure, complete NixOS installation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Why did we choose Nix?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We wanted IDX workspaces to work for any developer, anywhere. Part of our philosophy is to avoid proprietary tools, languages, or configuration models wherever we can. Beyond that, we want to contribute to the developer community whenever possible. Nix is widely available and community supported, so it made sense to build it into IDX as our configuration model. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the IDX-specific attributes and packages to define the preview environment in your browser-based workspace, you can depend on any &lt;a href=&quot;https://search.nixos.org/packages&quot;&gt;packages that are available on Nix&lt;/a&gt;. We wanted to support a tool that most of our engineers could use, and that could support the tools our developer users want.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, using Nix allowed us to add instant tooling to IDX. When you want to use a tool from the command line, all you have to do is run its command. If it&amp;#39;s not already installed in your environment, the terminal shows a prompt with available Nix packages exposing a command with that name. If you choose one, IDX then grabs the package behind the scenes and executes the command. Easy peasy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;How do you use Nix on IDX?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you create a new workspace, a &lt;code&gt;.idx&lt;/code&gt; folder with a &lt;code&gt;dev.nix&lt;/code&gt; file is automagically added to your root directory. (If it isn’t, you can create it yourself to enable Nix.) You can define packages and your preview environment configuration here, following the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nix.dev/tutorials/first-steps/nix-language#attribute-set&quot;&gt;Nix attribute set syntax&lt;/a&gt;. You can see a list of IDX-specific packages and a detailed sample in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/customize-idx-env#nix_attributes_and_package_libraries&quot;&gt;IDX technical documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What’s next for Nix on IDX?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We firmly believe that the sky’s the limit for flexibility and extensibility in IDX workspaces, and we’re working hard to boost productivity for our developers — and ourselves — as much as possible. We recently also made it easier to edit &lt;code&gt;dev.nix&lt;/code&gt; files thanks to syntax highlighting, auto-completion and error detection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, we’re hoping to add even more templates to make startup and setup even easier and faster for common workspace setups. Because, as we might’ve mentioned once or twice, we here at Project IDX like to work fast.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Post</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/jan-update-thread/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/jan-update-thread/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday we announced new features in Project IDX&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;📱 Android Emulator &amp;amp; iOS Simulator in browser&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;💻 A template gallery ready for your new projects&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;🐳 Docker in a single line of code&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;🌎 AI in 15 new regions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;⚡ Instantly run CLI tools&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;⬇️ Here&amp;#39;s a wrap up of everything you need to know&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Introducing Android emulators, iOS simulators, and other product updates from Project IDX</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/introducing-android-emulators-ios-simulators-and-other-product-updates-from/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/introducing-android-emulators-ios-simulators-and-other-product-updates-from/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Six months ago, we &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/blog/article/introducing-project-idx&quot;&gt;launched Project IDX&lt;/a&gt;, an experimental, cloud-based workspace for full-stack, multiplatform software development. We built Project IDX to simplify and streamline the developer workflow, aiming to reduce the sea of complexities traditionally associated with app development. It certainly seems like we&amp;#39;ve piqued your interest, and we love seeing what IDX has helped you build.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, we recently learned about &lt;a href=&quot;https://lingonberry.ai/tanaki&quot;&gt;Tanaki&lt;/a&gt;, an AI-enhanced content creation app built using Project IDX:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/okpasquale&quot;&gt;Pasquale D’Silva&lt;/a&gt;, one of the developers that built Tanaki, said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Using the IDX shared workspace to build Tanaki has been so fun. It allows our remote team of imagineers to build together in one place. It is a magic collaboration portal!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Developers at Google have also been using IDX internally to help speed up development across various projects. One example is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.blog/&quot;&gt;Firebase Blog&lt;/a&gt;, where the full authoring, development, and deployment of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://astro.build/&quot;&gt;Astro&lt;/a&gt;-powered project is handled using IDX:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another interesting project leveraging IDX’s extensibility model is &lt;a href=&quot;http://malloydata.dev&quot;&gt;Malloy&lt;/a&gt;, a new open-source data language available as a VS Code extension that operates against databases like BigQuery:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lloyd Tabb, a Distinguished Software Engineer at Google, told us: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I use IDX with the &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://malloydata.dev&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Malloy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt; project. I often have several different data projects going simultaneously and IDX lets me quickly spin up an instance to solve a problem and it is trivial to configure.&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to share what IDX has helped you build, use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ProjectIDX?src=hashtag_click&quot;&gt;#ProjectIDX&lt;/a&gt; tag on X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What’s new in IDX?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to seeing how you’re using IDX, a key part of building Project IDX &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com&quot;&gt;is your feedback&lt;/a&gt;, so we’ve continued to roll out features for you to test. We&amp;#39;re excited to share the latest updates we&amp;#39;ve implemented to expedite and streamline multiplatform app development, so you can deliver with speed, ease and quality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Preview your app directly in IDX with our iOS simulator and Android emulator&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re bringing the iOS Simulator and Android Emulator to the browser. Whether you’re building a Flutter or web app, Project IDX now allows you to preview your applications without having to leave your workspace. When you use a Flutter or web template, Project IDX intelligently loads the right preview environment for your application — Safari mobile and Chrome for web templates, or Android, iOS, and Chrome for Flutter templates.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX’s web and Android emulators allow you to develop, test, and debug directly from your workspace, consolidating your multi-step, multiplatform process into one place. With iOS simulation you can spot-check your app&amp;#39;s layout and behavior while you work. This feature is still experimental, so be sure to test it out and &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com/forums/953956-general&quot;&gt;send us feedback&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Get started fast with a rich library of project templates&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four of our top ten &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com/forums/953956-general?status_id=5378749&quot;&gt;feature requests&lt;/a&gt; have been to support more templates, so we’re pleased to share that we’ve added new templates for Astro, Go, Python/Flask, Qwik, Lit, Preact, Solid.js, and Node.js. Use these templates to jump right into your project so you can spend less time setting up and more time creating. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course you can still import your own repo from GitHub, directly from your local files, or you can choose your own setup using a custom Nix environment. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Quickly build and customize your IDX workspace with improvements to Nix &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX uses Nix to define the environment configuration for each workspace to give you flexibility and extensibility in IDX – even our templates and previews are configured using Nix to ensure they’re working correctly inside IDX. We’re continuously working on Nix improvements to help boost your productivity, so now you can: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Customize IDX starter templates easily by leveraging Nix extensibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reduce the likelihood of errors and write code more efficiently with Nix file editing, including support for syntax highlighting, error detection, and suggested code completions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recover from broken configurations quickly and avoid unnecessary rebuild attempts with major improvements to our environment customization workflow, including seamless environment rebuilds and troubleshooting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Easily build, test, and deploy apps with additional new IDX features and resources&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Auto-detect network ports needed for applications or services and adjust the firewall settings to permit ingress and egress without any additional configuration on your end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instantly run command-line tools, scripts, and utilities directly within your workspace without the need to install them locally on your machine. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Simplify the process of working with Docker containers and images directly from the development environment by enabling Docker in your dev.nix file.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;AI launched in 15 new regions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’ve launched our AI capabilities in the following 15 countries: India, Australia, Israel, Brazil, Mexico, Colombia, Argentina, Peru, Chile, Singapore, Bangladesh, Pakistan, Canada, Japan, and South Korea. More countries will be enabled with AI access soon – indicate your interest for AI expansion in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com/forums/953956-general/suggestions/46838062-expand-to-europe-and-other-regions&quot;&gt;feature tracking post&lt;/a&gt; and stay tuned for more AI updates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Improving together &lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re constantly working on adding new capabilities to help you do higher quality work, more efficiently, with less friction. We’ve addressed dozens of your feature requests and fixed a multitude of bugs you flagged for us, so thank you for your continued support and engagement – please keep the feedback coming by &lt;a href=&quot;https://issuetracker.google.com/issues/new?component=1379083&amp;template=1836320&quot;&gt;filing bugs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com/forums/953956-general&quot;&gt;feature requests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For walkthroughs and more information on all the features mentioned above, check out our &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/introduction&quot;&gt;documentation page&lt;/a&gt;. If you haven’t already, visit our website to &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/&quot;&gt;sign up to try Project IDX&lt;/a&gt; and join us on our journey. Also, be sure to check out our new &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/blog&quot;&gt;Project IDX Blog&lt;/a&gt; for the latest product announcements and updates from the team. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can’t wait to see what you create with Project IDX! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>How we built Project IDX: A high-level overview</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/how-we-built-project-idx-a-high-level-overview/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/how-we-built-project-idx-a-high-level-overview/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Project IDX is a browser-based development experience that we designed to make the end-to-end multi-platform app development workflow faster and more frictionless. We&amp;#39;re developers building a tool for developers, and we want to share a high-level overview of how we&amp;#39;ve built IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Goals: What we strive for&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before we get into the technical details powering IDX, let&amp;#39;s take a look at some of the lofty goals we have for IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Familiar and secure environment&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As soon as users visit IDX, we want to put them in a familiar and secure environment. To that end, IDX was built on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/microsoft/vscode&quot;&gt;Code OSS&lt;/a&gt;. Code OSS doesn&amp;#39;t just feel familiar to developers, it also has a great selection of extensions that you can bring in through &lt;a href=&quot;https://open-vsx.org/&quot;&gt;Open VSX&lt;/a&gt;. We enhanced Code OSS with our own customization (themes, tools, and plugins) to bring several unique features to IDX on top of basic Code OSS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Developers can be pretty particular about modifying their development environment (we are too!) and we wanted to support that. We have a strong affinity for the tools we&amp;#39;ve gradually mastered over the years to boost our productivity and we wouldn&amp;#39;t want to give them up. We knew when we decided to build a new tool that asking developers to embrace a completely unfamiliar environment would be an unrealistic expectation. Therefore, our aim was to incorporate Code OSS, ensuring that developers step into a familiar environment when they transition to IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Beyond prototypes&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We want developers to use IDX for more than just prototypes. We didn&amp;#39;t want to just put out a toy environment that only works for proof-of-concept apps. Every IDX workspace comes with a full Debian-based VM and provides full access to the terminal so you can install your favorite tools. VMs automatically hibernate and activate as needed. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX provides the convenience of using a VM without any of the headaches that come with managing infrastructure, security updates, billing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Batteries included&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because IDX comes with a full Debian VM, we&amp;#39;re able to preset the environment just right even before you write your first line of code. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take Flutter, for example: Our research shows that developers spend an average of 6 hours setting up their dev environment before they write the first lines of code. With IDX, you can get going in a Flutter environment with just one click. When you select a Flutter template, the workspace already has the Android SDK and Flutter tool chain set up. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.android.com/tools/adb&quot;&gt;Android Debug Bridge&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt;) connections are wired up. Flutter &amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot; are connected and work out-of-the-box. Everything is also connected back to your workspace so changes hot reload instantly and step-through debugging is set up without any configuration required. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Select different templates or create your own to get your environment to work the way you want it, with everything you need to get up and running quickly. You can always customize your workspace environment to your taste (it&amp;#39;s based on Code-OSS after all), but we aspire to be close to your perfect setup for the job at hand at the click of a button.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Integrated previews&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being web developers ourselves, we&amp;#39;re all used to setting up our development environment by:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;cd-ing into our folder&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Running the server (&lt;code&gt;npm run dev&lt;/code&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opening up the preview. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With IDX, we wanted to cut this down to even fewer steps, leading us to a preview within the workspace. Rather than switching different tabs or windows, we wanted to provide a way to instantly start coding in your workspace and see the results. An integrated preview also provides benefits during collaboration and opportunities to improve the debugging experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Collaboration&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Software development is akin to a team sport, whether you&amp;#39;re part of a larger team or a solo developer collaborating with a client. The availability of a seamless collaboration method is advantageous for everyone. If our tools like documents and spreadsheets can facilitate collaboration, why should our coding workspaces lag behind? In the creation of IDX, our aim was to prioritize and simplify collaboration and sharing, making it effortless for users to engage in activities like pair-programming and sharing code previews.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;AI-enabled&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are constantly exploring how Google&amp;#39;s AI innovations can help you write code faster. Project IDX has smart code completion, an assistive chatbot, and contextual code actions like &amp;quot;add comments&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;explain this code.&amp;quot; In collaboration with the models that power studio bot and Duet, we are working on making IDX AI even better in being a constant companion that helps you as you write code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Meet the community where they are&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We want to meet our developer community where they are. Because of that, IDX doesn&amp;#39;t rely on users knowing any Google-proprietary tech (eg., Bazel or Boq). We use the tools that are popular with developers today so we can boost productivity in those tools for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Technology: Behind the scenes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Google Cloud&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX workspaces are built on top of &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/workstations&quot;&gt;Google&amp;#39;s Cloud Workstations&lt;/a&gt; offering. Cloud workstations enable us to provision and scale VMs. We have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/workstations/docs/create-configuration&quot;&gt;custom workstation configuration&lt;/a&gt; that deploys our specially provisioned docker container when a new VM is spun up. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cloud Workstations formed the perfect infrastructure layer for our production because:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It allows us to spin up VMs on demand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s fast, secure, and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It allows us to configure a base environment specially designed for IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;AI models&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI features of IDX are powered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/docs/generative-ai/code/code-models-overview&quot;&gt;codey&lt;/a&gt; and Gemini. The same models also power &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.android.com/studio/preview/studio-bot&quot;&gt;Studio Bot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/application-modernization/introducing-duet-ai-for-google-cloud&quot;&gt;Duet&lt;/a&gt;. Different models power different AI features. For example a 12b model powers our code completion while a 24b model powers streaming conversation and code generation features. As more powerful models are being developed within Google, we&amp;#39;ll incorporate them to make IDX AI even better at helping you work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To learn more about our AI features, read our &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/code-with-idx-ai&quot;&gt;IDX AI product documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Managing Previews&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In line with the batteries-included approach, we want to get you productive within seconds of creating an IDX workspace. An IDX workspace doesn&amp;#39;t just start up with your code, but also with the preview already running (when applicable).  A preview server running on your VM manages your previews. In most cases, this allows you to immediately start making changes to your code and see the change &amp;quot;hot reload&amp;quot; in the preview as soon as your workspace is created. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The preview server exposes controls that allow you to hot reload the previews as you change the code and execute commands like &amp;quot;Hard Restart&amp;quot; that would stop your preview and fully restart it. Learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/preview-apps&quot;&gt;previews in IDX in our documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Environment Setup&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, IDX workspaces are built on top of Google Cloud Workstations which allow us to spin up our custom &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; containers. Within these containers, we package various system software such as tools for running services, scheduling jobs (such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://supervisord.org/&quot;&gt;Supervisor&lt;/a&gt;), and other custom written jobs such as preview server.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To keep our Docker containers small and easier to maintain, we keep separate containers for web and mobile stacks (Flutter). When you create a new workspace, Google Cloud Workstation brings up our container and executes the entrypoint script responsible for setting up everything you need to start coding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Service Account-based authentication&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that workspaces are shared, we want a way to securely connect your VM with other services. This is done through &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/iam/docs/service-account-overview&quot;&gt;Service Accounts&lt;/a&gt;. Every workspace is set up with a unique service account that only has enough permissions to communicate with authorized services from that VM. A custom &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/compute/docs/metadata/overview&quot;&gt;metadata server&lt;/a&gt; running on the VM securely manages this access. Access to the service account is only provisioned based on explicit requests from the user. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Nix&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our pursuit of offering versatile and highly customizable workspaces for diverse development needs, we have made it one of our goals to support various popular programming stacks like Node.js, Python, Rust, and Go. To achieve this, we extensively explored different options that would enable us to deliver a user-friendly and flexible environment without imposing excessive maintenance burdens on our team. After careful consideration, we concluded that adopting Nix as our solution would best align with our objectives. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nixos.org/&quot;&gt;Nix&lt;/a&gt; is a purely functional package manager and build system that provides reproducibility, atomic upgrades and rollbacks, isolation, sandboxing, and package versioning and conflict resolution. By ensuring explicit and isolated dependencies, Nix allows for consistent and predictable builds across different systems and over time. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX uses Nix as a way to provide this flexibility to developers while reducing the complexity and the learning curve that comes with learning a new configuration language. Learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/idx/guides/customize-idx-env#nix+idx&quot;&gt;Nix + IDX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;High-level architecture&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Further details&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This blog post only covers the very high-level details of IDX. In further blog posts, we&amp;#39;ll discuss each area in detail, the technical details and challenges in developing those features. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Where are we going?&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sharing and collaboration&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although we aspire to achieve the level of seamless sharing and collaboration found in Google Docs, we are aware that we have a significant journey ahead of us. Our objective is to create a platform that enables developers to effortlessly collaborate with both technical and non-technical team members, facilitating activities such as preview sharing and pair programming. While real-time editing and commenting features are currently in our roadmap, we acknowledge that there is work to be done to fulfill our goal of providing a comprehensive and user-friendly collaborative environment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;More AI features&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is clear to us that we are only on day-1 for AI when it comes to helping developers. Currently, Project IDX has smart code completion, an assistive chatbot, and contextual code actions like &amp;quot;add comments&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;explain this code.&amp;quot;  We are exploring several ways to use the power of generative AI to help you code including (but not limited to) the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write and edit code with AI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let AI understand your code base better and suggest changes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let AI understand docs specific to your code base and answer questions based on that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let AI automatically debug and fix issues with your code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let AI pair program with you helping your write better/safer code and tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;More customization&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;As shared earlier, one of our key design goals was to enable developers to build and be productive on all kinds of stacks on Project IDX. All of this will be powered by Nix, so developers will have the ability to bring their stack of choice and get productive. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Get Involved&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are just at the beginning of this journey to improve the end-to-end development workflow, and we can only make good on this vision with your help. Get involved by &lt;a href=&quot;http://idx.dev&quot;&gt;joining our waitlist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://idx.uservoice.com&quot;&gt;requesting features&lt;/a&gt;! Let&amp;#39;s build this together!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>New Gemini template</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/new-gemini-template/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/new-gemini-template/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;💜 Rolling out soon and already available for some in Project IDX: a new multimodal Gemini template (&lt;code&gt;gemini-pro-vision&lt;/code&gt;) in JS and Python!&lt;i&gt; (Attached video skips a couple steps, e.g. getting your API key from Google AI Studio).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Want to try out Project IDX? &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev/#waitlist&quot;&gt;Join the waitlist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Generate TypeScript Types</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/generate-ts-types/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/generate-ts-types/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;🔮 &lt;b&gt;IDX AI + TypeScript tip!&lt;/b&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Take a nested JSON object and prompt for the types. You&amp;#39;ll get the parent type with all the children types specified as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Welcome to the IDX Blog!</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/welcome-to-the-idx-blog/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/welcome-to-the-idx-blog/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Today, we are so excited to ship our official Project IDX blog out to the world. We&amp;#39;re not just excited because we think that every good developer tool needs a blog. We&amp;#39;re excited for what&amp;#39;s in store.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;All IDX updates. In one place.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IDX Blog is going to be more than a spot for the occasional blog or product update. We want to keep you informed on progress we’re making, even when features aren’t fully baked or even ready for release, so we’ll post here often. When we &lt;a href=&quot;./introducing-project-idx&quot;&gt;first launched Project IDX back in August&lt;/a&gt;, it was an early look; the blog will help us continue to show you where we&amp;#39;re headed. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We built this blog to support a variety of different content forms: from long-form posts to social-style posts and short videos so you can get a quick peek into a feature in development, a video overview of a new use case, or a technical deep dive on a more advanced concept. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Often, you&amp;#39;ll find this content spread out across different platforms. Blogs on the blog. Videos on YouTube. Social posts on social media sites. We created this blog to be the place for all content and updates with &lt;a href=&quot;../rss.xml&quot;&gt;one feed to subscribe to it all&lt;/a&gt;, because RSS will never go out of style.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Long-form posts&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the IDX team, we are passionate about knowledge sharing. We have an amazing weekly &amp;quot;Show and Tell&amp;quot; meeting where we demo new concepts and the status of upcoming features. It becomes a place to learn more about the engineering behind the scenes as well. We want to take this internal passion and share it externally with you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll be posting Engineering blogs that go behind the scenes about how specific IDX features work and even some of the technology that powers it as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Tips, tricks, and more&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes all you need is 244 characters. IDX is young but already has so many features that we want to share with you. Did you know that IDX AI can write unit tests for you? Or that you can build a custom environment to develop on Go, Rust, PHP, or Python?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re going to be posting new content ranging from technical deep dives to byte-sized posts about all the things you can do with IDX and other awesome tools like Angular, Flutter, Go, Firebase, and much more. Again, If you want to stay up to date check out our RSS feed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Our blog stack&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a developer finally ships their blog, it&amp;#39;s almost a law that the very first post needs to be about how the blog was made.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Astro with View Transitions&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This blog is built on our existing &lt;a href=&quot;https://astro.build&quot;&gt;Astro&lt;/a&gt; site and backed by a headless CMS. Astro makes building content-based sites a breeze. We wanted to take advantage of Astro&amp;#39;s View Transition API features to create smooth transitions from page to page. Huge shoutout to the Astro team for making such a great tool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Deployed on Firebase&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though the transition feels like a Single Page Application (SPA) the entire site is a statically generated Multi-Page Application (MPA) deployed on Firebase Hosting using the Web Frameworks integration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Check back for more content and updates&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first post of many updates to come. Next week we&amp;#39;re releasing a blog about the underlying architecture of Project IDX itself. Make sure to subscribe to the RSS feed and reach out to us on social media if you want us to post about any specific topics. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We built Project IDX because we want to work with you to make multiplatform app development better, so please give the feedback and suggestions coming either through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.uservoice.com&quot;&gt;Feature Requests portal&lt;/a&gt; or by &lt;a href=&quot;https://b.corp.google.com/issues/new?component=1379083&amp;template=1836320&quot;&gt;filing bugs&lt;/a&gt;. We can&amp;#39;t wait to see what you&amp;#39;ll build with Project IDX.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Full-stack development in Project IDX</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/full-stack-development-in-project-idx/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/full-stack-development-in-project-idx/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We launched Project IDX, our new browser-based development experience, to simplify the chaos of building full stack apps and streamline the development process from (back)end to (front)end. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our experience, most web applications are built with at-least two different layers: a frontend (UI) layer and a backend layer. When you think about the kind of app you’d build in a browser-based developer workspace, you might not immediately jump to full-stack apps with robust, fully functional backends. Developing a backend in a web-based environment can get clunky and costly very quickly. Between different authentication setups for development and production environments, secure communication between backend and frontend, and the complexity of setting up a fully self-contained (hermetic) testing environment, costs and inconveniences can add up. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We know a lot of you are excited to try IDX yourselves, but in the meantime, we wanted to share this post about full-stack development in Project IDX. We’ll untangle some of the complex situations you might hit as a developer building both your frontend and backend layers in a web-based workspace — developer authentication, frontend-backend communication, and hermetic testing — and how we’ve tried to make it all just a little bit easier. And of course we want to hear from you about what else we should build that would make full-stack development easier for you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Streamlined app previews&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, we&amp;#39;ve streamlined the process of enabling your applications frontend communication with its backend services in the VM, making it effortless to preview your full-stack application in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IDX workspaces are built on Google Cloud Workstations and securely access connected services through &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/iam/docs/service-account-overview&quot;&gt;Service Accounts&lt;/a&gt;. Each workspace’s unique service account supports seamless, authenticated preview environments for your applications frontend. So, when you use Project IDX, application previews are built directly into your workspace, and you don’t actually have to set up a different authentication path to preview your UI. Currently, IDX only supports web previews, but Android and iOS application previews are coming soon to IDX workspaces near you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if your setup necessitates communication with the backend API under development in IDX from outside the browser preview, we&amp;#39;ve established a few mechanisms to temporarily provide access to the ports hosting these API backends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Simple front-to-backend communication&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re using a framework that serves both the backend and frontend layers from the same port, you can pass the $PORT flag to use a custom PORT environment variable in your workspace configuration file (powered by Nix and stored directly in your workspace). This is part of the basic setup flow in Project IDX, so you don’t have to do anything particularly special (outside of setting the variable in your config file). Here’s an example Nix-based configuration file:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;type: embedded-entry-inline id: 6iey3INRLrC9ZQc7TPmnKy&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, if your backend server is running on a different port from your UI server, you’ll need to implement a different strategy.  One method is to have the frontend proxy the backend, as you would with &lt;a href=&quot;https://vitejs.dev/config/server-options.html&quot;&gt;Vite&amp;#39;s custom server options&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another way to establish communication between ports is to set up your code so the javascript running on your UI can communicate with the backend server using AJAX requests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with some sample code that includes both a backend and a frontend. Here’s a backend server written in Express.js:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;type: embedded-entry-inline id: nAf2R7kYSr65cwYE9PqDi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bolded line in the sample — &lt;code&gt;app.use(cors());&lt;/code&gt; —  sets up the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/CORS&quot;&gt;CORS headers&lt;/a&gt;. Set up might be different based on the language/framework of your choice, but your backend needs to return these headers whether you’re developing locally or on IDX. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you run the server in the IDX terminal, the backend ports show up in the IDX panel. And every port that your server runs on is automatically mapped to a URL you can call.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;#39;s write some client code to make an AJAX call to this server.

&lt;span&gt;type: embedded-entry-inline id: 1TFwWPKbrrNzaBoOtGecXK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’ve also made sure that the &lt;code&gt;fetch()&lt;/code&gt; call includes credentials. IDX urls are authenticated, so we need to include credentials. This way, the AJAX call includes the cookies to authenticate against our servers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re using &lt;code&gt;XMLHttpRequest&lt;/code&gt; instead of fetch, you can set the “&lt;code&gt;withCredentials&lt;/code&gt;” property, like this:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;type: embedded-entry-inline id: 3xkFSTeYRdTtkp5NCAa7J4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your code might differ from our samples based on the client library you use to make the AJAX calls. If it does, check the documentation for your specific client library on how to make a credentialed request. Just be sure to make a credentialed request. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Server-side testing without a login&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In some cases you might want to access your application on Project IDX without logging into your Google account — or from an environment where you &lt;i&gt;can’t &lt;/i&gt;log into your Google account. For example, if you want to access an API you&amp;#39;re developing in IDX using either Postman or cURL from your personal laptops&amp;#39;s command line. You can do this by using a temporary access token generated by Project IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once you have a server running in Project IDX, you can bring up the command menu to generate an access token. This access token is a short-lived token that temporarily allows you to access your workstation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s extremely important to note that this access token provides access to your entire IDX workspace, including but not limited to your application in preview, so you shouldn’t share it with just anyone. We recommend that you only use it for testing. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you run this command from IDX, your access token shows up in a dialog window. Copy the access token and use it to make a cURL request to a service running on your workstation, like this one:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;type: embedded-entry-inline id: 4473NZtcGuV9pv28Pbj0pZ&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And now you can run tests from an authenticated server environment! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Web-based, fully hermetic testing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we’ve highlighted, you can test your application’s frontend and backend in a fully self-contained, authenticated, secure environment using IDX. You can &lt;i&gt;also&lt;/i&gt; run local emulators in your web-based development environment to test your application’s backend services. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, you can run the &lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/docs/emulator-suite&quot;&gt;Firebase Local Emulator Suite&lt;/a&gt; directly from your IDX workspace. To &lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/docs/emulator-suite/install_and_configure&quot;&gt;install the emulator suite&lt;/a&gt;, you’d run firebase init emulators from the IDX &lt;i&gt;Terminal&lt;/i&gt; tab and follow the steps to configure which emulators you want on what ports.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve installed them, you can configure and use them the same way you would in a local development environment from the IDX terminal. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see, Project IDX can meet any and all of your development needs — from frontend to backend and every emulator in between.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Nix in the Wild: Project IDX</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/nix-in-the-wild-project-idx/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/nix-in-the-wild-project-idx/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;a href=&quot;https://nixos.org/&quot;&gt;Nix&lt;/a&gt; at Project IDX to manage development environments. Nix is an open source environment manager that is fast, scalable, and deterministic. With Nix, there&amp;#39;s no more &amp;quot;it works on my machine&amp;quot; problems. Nix may not be a tool you&amp;#39;ve heard of before, but it&amp;#39;s been invaluable for us. In this interview I go into details about how we Nix to power IDX development environments, ensuring that everyone on the team is using the same tools and versions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Generate TypeScript types, unit tests, and JSDoc comments with Project IDX AI</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/generate-typescript-types-unit-tests-and-jsdoc-comments-with-project-idx-ai/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/generate-typescript-types-unit-tests-and-jsdoc-comments-with-project-idx-ai/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Generative AI is full of time savers. The AI Chat in Project IDX has a contextual understanding of your codebase and can help you generate TypeScript types, write unit tests, and documentation based comments like JSDoc.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Project IDX on Syntax.fm</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/project-idx-on-syntax-fm/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/project-idx-on-syntax-fm/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s the experience of Project IDX? I had an incredible chat on &lt;a href=&quot;https://syntax.fm/show/676/google-idx-vs-code-in-the-browser-with-david-east&quot;&gt;Syntax.fm&lt;/a&gt; discussing the details of IDX. We go over Flutter apps on IDX, how we use nix for custom environments, latency in cloud environments, project sharing, extensions, and a whole lot more.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Project IDX, Cloud-Based Development, Future of Coding - with Roman Nurik</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/project-idx-cloud-based-development-future-of-coding-with-roman-nurik/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/project-idx-cloud-based-development-future-of-coding-with-roman-nurik/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Will your future development environment be entirely based in the cloud? I had a chat with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/codepo8&quot;&gt;Chris Heilmann&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wearedevelopers.com/&quot;&gt;WeAreDevelopers&lt;/a&gt; about what the future of coding looks like and the shift from local environments to cloud based ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Project IDX: Full-stack application development with generative AI</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/post/project-idx-full-stack-application-development-with-generative-ai/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/post/project-idx-full-stack-application-development-with-generative-ai/</guid><description>📢 Post</description><pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Project IDX is still in early development but we wanted to share a preview of it&amp;#39;s current capabilities. We just posted a video that covers project creation, terminal commands, deployment, environment customization, and generative AI for coding tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Introducing Project IDX, An Experiment to Improve Full-stack, Multiplatform App Development</title><link>https://idx.dev/blog/article/introducing-project-idx/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://idx.dev/blog/article/introducing-project-idx/</guid><description>🔖 Article</description><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;These days, getting an app from zero to production–especially one that works well across mobile, web, and desktop platforms–can feel like building a Rube Goldberg machine.  You’ve got to navigate an endless sea of complexity, duct-taping together a tech stack that&amp;#39;ll help you bootstrap, compile, test, deploy, and monitor your apps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Google’s been working on making multiplatform app development easier for years—from &lt;a href=&quot;https://angular.dev&quot;&gt;Angular&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://flutter.dev/&quot;&gt;Flutter&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Cloud&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com&quot;&gt;Firebase&lt;/a&gt;—it feels like &lt;b&gt;there’s even more we can do to make the entire multiplatform app development workflow faster and more frictionless.&lt;/b&gt; So several months ago, a few of us got together and started experimenting. And today, we’re excited to share a very early look at our experiment, which we’re calling &lt;a href=&quot;idx.dev&quot;&gt;Project IDX&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Project IDX is a browser-based development experience built on Google Cloud Workstations and powered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/docs/generative-ai/code/code-models-overview&quot;&gt;Codey&lt;/a&gt;, a foundational AI model trained on code and built on PaLM 2. It’s designed to make it easier to build, manage and deploy full-stack web and multiplatform applications, with popular frameworks and languages. Project IDX is also built on Code OSS, so it should feel familiar no matter what you’re building.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A big part of why we’re sharing Project IDX today is we’d love to hear from the broader developer community on what could help you work even faster. In the meantime, here’s a preview of what’s possible today with Project IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Get to work quickly, from anywhere&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the heart of Project IDX is our conviction that you should be able to develop from anywhere, on any device, with the full fidelity of local development. Every Project IDX workspace has the full capabilities of a Linux-based VM, paired with the universal access that comes with being hosted in the cloud, in a datacenter near you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Import your existing app, or start something new&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Project IDX lets you import your existing projects from GitHub so you can pick up right where you left off. You can also create new projects, with pre-baked templates for popular frameworks, including Angular, Flutter, Next.js, React, Svelte, Vue, and languages such as JavaScript, Dart, and (coming soon) Python, Go, and more. We’re also actively working to add first-class support for more project types and frameworks. If you have any suggestions, we’d love your feedback on which stacks to support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Preview your app across platforms&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating successful apps today means optimizing your app design and behavior across platforms, and previewing your apps just as your users would see them. To make this easier, Project IDX includes a built-in web preview and, coming soon, a fully-configured Android emulator and an embedded iOS simulator, all available directly in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Help from AI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We spend a lot of time writing code, and recent advances in AI have created big opportunities to make that time more productive. With Project IDX, we’re exploring how Google’s innovations in AI—including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/docs/generative-ai/code/code-models-overview&quot;&gt;Codey&lt;/a&gt; and PaLM 2 models powering &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.android.com/studio/preview/studio-bot&quot;&gt;Studio Bot&lt;/a&gt; in Android Studio, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/application-modernization/introducing-duet-ai-for-google-cloud&quot;&gt;Duet in Google Cloud&lt;/a&gt; and more—can help you not only write code faster, but also write higher-quality code. Currently, Project IDX has smart code completion, an assistive chatbot, and contextual code actions like “add comments” and “explain this code”. Our AI capabilities are in their very early days, and we’re working on making IDX AI even better at helping you as you work&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Publish to the web with Firebase Hosting&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, a common pain point in getting your app into production is deploying it. We’ve made this easier by integrating &lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/products/hosting&quot;&gt;Firebase Hosting&lt;/a&gt;, making it possible to deploy a shareable preview of your web app, or deploy to production with a fast, secure, and global hosting platform, with just a few clicks. And because Firebase Hosting supports dynamic backends, powered by Cloud Functions, this works great for full-stack frameworks like Next.js.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;b&gt;Let’s build Project IDX together&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We shared how we think Project IDX can start to make multiplatform app development better, along with some strides we’ve started making in these areas. But we are just at the beginning of this journey to improve the end-to-end development workflow, and we can only make good on this vision with your help. So with that, we’d like to share an early version of Project IDX with you—rough edges and all—to iterate on what’s working well and what could be even better for your app team’s workflow. To join us on our journey, &lt;a href=&quot;https://idx.dev&quot;&gt;visit our website&lt;/a&gt; to sign up and be one of the first to try Project IDX.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As for what’s next, we’re continuously working on adding new capabilities and addressing your feedback. We’re already working on new collaboration features, as we know how important those are in this hybrid work world, as well as deeper framework integrations and more personalized/contextual AI. Please share your feature requests with us as well!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>